<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks on the preface to The Protestant reconciler in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>S. T. (Samuel Thomas), 1627-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25646</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09053526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09053526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1296:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks on the preface to The Protestant reconciler in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>S. T. (Samuel Thomas), 1627-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>61 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Wallis for Joanna Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: S.T.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitby, Daniel, 1638-1726. --  Protestant reconciler.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42329:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REMARKS ON THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>Proteſtant Reconciler:</hi> IN A LETTER TO A FRIEND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Wallis,</hi> for <hi>Joanna Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:42329:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42329:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving Read and Conſider'd the Preface to [<hi>The Proteſtant Reconciler</hi>] I now ſend you theſe Remarks upon it.</p>
            <p>The Author profeſſes <hi>Pag.</hi> 58. (of that <hi>Preface</hi>) That he does from his heart Conform to all that is requir'd by the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and yet a great part of the Preface is employ'd in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Teſtimonies againſt the Lawfulneſs not only of [the Impoſition it ſelf] but alſo of [the things Impos'd;] we are told <hi>p.</hi> 25. out of <hi>Beza</hi>'s Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Grindal,</hi> That <hi>Men ſo oft do grievouſly Sin, as they do introduce into the Church of God any Ceremonies ſignificative of Spiritual things,</hi> and <hi>that all Symbolical Rites ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely excluded from the Chriſtian Church;</hi> And this (forſooth) muſt have a Hand ſet over againſt it in the margin, as if it ought to be taken for ſome very precious and valuable Truth.</p>
            <p>We are told alſo by the ſame Divine, <hi>p.</hi> 26. That <hi>the Right of Croſſing is not to be reckon'd among things Indifferent, but</hi> (as a thing) <hi>rather to be deſtroyed than the brazen Serpent of</hi> Hezekias. That <hi>they do beſt of all who are as diligent in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42329:3"/>
Aboliſhing the Rites of Croſſing in Baptiſm, and Kneeling at the Sacrament, as they would be in Aboliſhing open Idolatry.</hi> And this alſo is thought fit to be Printed in another Character, and to be mark'd out with a marginal Hand, as if 'twere a Maxim of Infallible Truth.</p>
            <p>A great many other Reproaches of our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and their Impoſition, are tranſcribed into the following Pages; as <hi>p.</hi> 27. That <hi>the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Ceremonies, is a falling back to worſe than the Ceremonies of</hi> Moſes; <hi>to the Trifles and Refuſe of human Traditions.</hi> That <hi>Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was carry'd with a Zeal not according to Knowledge, in Commanding the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them. Pag.</hi> 28. And that <hi>by that Impoſition, the Fire of Contention was to the incredible offence of the Godly, as it were raiſed from Hell.</hi> That <hi>the white Linen Garments requir'd to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſed in Divine Service, are at the leaſt ſigns of Idolatry, and Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.—with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe whereof Miniſters defile themſelves, and give offence to the Weak by their Example.</hi>—That <hi>to retain thoſe Garments is to deſtroy the whole Body of the Church</hi>—That <hi>they ought not be Impoſed (Pag. 30.) becauſe all things are to be abandon'd which may any way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either by themſelves or by accident, deſile Gods Worſhip,</hi>—becauſe <hi>they are contrary to the Purity of the Apoſtolical Worſhip, and ſmell of Popiſh Superſtion;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42329:3"/>
and are neither available to the Edification of the Godly, nor to Order, nor for Ornament, except that which is Whoriſh.</hi>—Becauſe <hi>all Godly men will be offended with the Decree concerning Apparel.</hi>—And, <hi>it may much further <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, and at leaſt give occaſion of many Evils, and very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Superſtitions: and the very Occaſions of Evils are to be ſhun'd,—becauſe 'tis God's Will (p. 31.) That after the Death of Chriſt, all Garments of</hi> Aaron <hi>and</hi> Levi <hi>ſhould be Aboliſh'd.—That the Lord himſelf Commanded that all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly and Vain Ceremonies ſhould be driven away, when he charg'd utterly to deſtroy all things which appertain'd to thoſe who ſhould give Counſel to follow ſtrange Gods; and to burn their Garments and all their Stuff, with Fire, that they might be an execrable thing unto the Lord.</hi>—Becauſe the Impoſing them <hi>miniſters Offence to the Conſciences of Weak Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,—which to do is very grievous and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtful to the Holy Spirit:</hi> and that <hi>Paul's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of reſolving always to abſtain from Fleſh rather than offend his Brother, gives a general Rule taken out of the Doctrin of Chriſt,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That no Indifferent thing is to be admitted, and yielded to, much leſs to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rg'd upon others, and leaſt of all to be Commanded by Decree, if in the Admitting, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rging, and Commanding of it, the Minds of Good Men, and Conſciences of the Faithful be Offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42329:4"/>Now this <hi>Prefacer</hi> did either look upon theſe kind of (paultry) Argumentations againſt our Ceremonies, and their Impoſition, and theſe and a great many other Cenſorious Reproaches of them, as Valid Arguings, and Juſtifiable Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or he did not; if he did not, to what end has he taken the Pains to Tranſcribe them? un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he had a Fanatick Deſign of rendring our Church and State-Conſtitutions, odious by ſo doing? But if he does really judge them Valid and Juſtifiable, he is a ſtrange Man that can <hi>from his heart</hi> Conform to all that is required by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet imagine not only [the impoſing and requiring] the Uſe of its Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies to be both without and againſt the Command of God, but alſo [the things requir'd and impos'd] to be ſome of them <hi>Signs of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and Popiſh Superſtition; that Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file themſelves with the uſe of them,—that they are only for Whoriſh Ornament; and ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the Minds of Good Men, and the Conſciences of the Faithful are Offended; and that ſuch things ought not, for that very reaſon, either to be Impoſed, or ſo much as Admitted, or Yielded to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if he has Tranſcribed them as Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, in his own Opinion juſtifiable, he has by quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe Paſſages out of other Writings, made them his own; And he has too plainly done ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42329:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in his re-capitulation, <hi>p.</hi> 43. where he expreſly Affirms, That <hi>judicious</hi> Beza [<hi>truly] ſaith, that theſe things (viz.</hi> Ceremonies required by the Church of <hi>England,) are not only unneceſſary, but profitable for little if a Man uſe them aright.</hi> And (as if this were not Reproach enough) this <hi>Prefacer</hi> has no more Wit nor Judgement than to Add, <hi>and when they [Accidentally] do miniſter to Schiſnt and all its fatal Conſequences:</hi> and then again to Approve it as <hi>truly ſaid by</hi> Beza, <hi>That to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuch Ceremonies, is to labour about Hay and Stubble, or rather, things more vain than they:</hi> And himſelf Affirms, That <hi>ſad Experience ſhews, that they bring no Profit, but many Evils to the Church: and that 'tis our Duty to ſhun the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe Evils.</hi> By which Approbation of, and Compliance with theſe Cenſures of things required and impoſed in our Church, I humbly conceive he has incurr'd the Penalty of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which is Decreed by <hi>Can.</hi> 4. againſt thoſe <hi>who Affirm that the Form of Gods Worſhip in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>Eſtabliſhed by Law, and Contained in the Book of Common-Prayer, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, is a Corrupt, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Worſhip of God, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth any thing in it that is repugnant to the Scriptures.</hi> By Can. 6. againſt thoſe <hi>Who Affirm that the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42329:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
England, <hi>by Law Eſtabliſhed, are Wicked, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, or Superſtitious.</hi> By <hi>Can.</hi> 10. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentially, For that Canon Excommunicated thoſe Separatiſts from the Church of <hi>England, who take upon them the Name of another Church, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to publiſh that this their pretended Church hath a long time Groaned under the Burden of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Grievances, impoſed upon the Members thereof, by the Church of</hi> England. And 'tis the drift of this Man's Preface and Book, to load the Church it ſelf with the Burden of this Reproachful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Opinion which this Prefacer owns as true, That <hi>the Ceremonies required in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>do bring no Profit, but many Evils to the Church,</hi> is a flat Contradiction to the Doctrin of the <hi>30th. Canon,</hi> touching the Uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, (<hi>viz.) That the Chriſtians ſhortly after the Apoſtles Time, uſed it in all their Actions, thereby making an outward Shew and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, even to the Aſtoniſhment of the Jews, that they were not aſhamed to Acknowledge Him for their Lord and Saviour, who Dyed for them upon the Croſs. And this Sign they did not only uſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a kind of Glory, when they met with any</hi> Jews; <hi>but ſigned therewith their Children when they were Chriſtned, to dedicate them by that Badge to His Service whoſe Benefits beſtowed upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42329:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them in Baptiſm, the Name of the Croſs did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent; and this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Sign of the Croſs in Baptiſm was held in the Primitive Church, as well by the</hi> Greeks <hi>as the</hi> Latins, <hi>with one conſent and great applauſe: at what time if any had oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt it, they would certainly have been Cenſur'd as Enemies of the Name of the Croſs, and conſequently of Chriſts Merits, the ſign whereof they could no better endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what muſt this <hi>Prefacer</hi> then be counted, who in complyance with Father <hi>Beza,</hi> Father <hi>Zanchy,</hi> and Father <hi>Calvin,</hi> (as he pretends <hi>Pag.</hi> 23.) Cenſur'd this and other Ceremonies as <hi>Fooleries,</hi> and the endeavouring to uphold them, as Labouring about Hay and Stubble, or rather about things more vain than they: and brands them as things bringing no Profit, but many Evils to the Church: whereas this Canon you ſee, expreſly teaches the contrary; and tho' it Acknowledges that <hi>in proceſs of time the ſign of the Croſs was greatly abuſed in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>eſpecially after the Corruption of Popery had once poſſeſſed it, yet withal it affirms that the Abuſe of a thing doth not take away the Lawful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of it. Nay ſo far was it from the purpoſe of the Church of</hi> England, (ſays the Canon,) <hi>to forſake and reject the Churches of</hi> Italy, France, Spain, Germany, <hi>or any ſuch like Churches, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42329:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all things which they held and practiſed, that as the Apology of the Church of</hi> England <hi>confeſſeth, it doth with reverence retain thoſe Ceremonies which do neither endamage the Church of God, nor offend the minds of Sober Men. In which reſpect, among ſome other very Ancient Ceremonies, the ſign of the Croſs in Baptiſm, hath been retained in the Church. For the very remembrance of the Croſs, which is very precious to all them that rightly Believe in Jeſus Chriſt, and in the other reſpects mention'd, the Church of</hi> England <hi>hath retained ſtill the ſign of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>in Baptiſm; following therein the Primitive and Apoſtolical Churches, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it a Lawful, Outward Ceremony, and Honourable Badge, whereby the Infant is Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Service of Him that dy'd upon the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I obſerve that this Prefacer confeſſes, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. that the Biſhops themſelves have no Power to diſpenſe with the Laws [for Uniformity] or <hi>to make any Propoſals for the healing of our Breaches:</hi> and if they have no ſuch Power, I wonder upon what grounds this Author aſſumes to himſelf the Power of making ſuch Propoſals; and ſuch as would deſtroy the Act of Uniformity, and Metamorphoſe the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> into a <hi>Directory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know he has produced the Teſtimony of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42329:6"/>
King <hi>James,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to juſtifie the deſign of his Book; but with how little Reaſon, Candor, and Ingenuity he has done it, I ſhall leave you to judge when you have conſider'd the reflexions I have to make upon them.</p>
            <p>As to that of K. <hi>James,</hi> it may ſuffice 1. To remember that notwithſtanding that excellent determination (as the <hi>Prefacer</hi> ſtyles it) his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was ſo far from changing, or antiquating, or ſo much as diſpenſing with the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that he ratified them anew, and gave thoſe Divines who appear'd againſt them at the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> a Severe Reprimand for ſcrupling Conformity to them upon ſuch inconſiderable Reaſons as were then urg'd for thoſe Scruples; and this Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he continued all his Reign.</p>
            <p>2. To take Notice that whereas this Writer calls that which <hi>Caſaubon</hi> repreſents as K. <hi>James</hi> his Opinion [<hi>a golden Sentence</hi>] and which fully juſtifies all which he pleads for; the words of that Golden Sentence as quoted by himſelf, do only affirm, That thoſe things which by the Conſtitutions of Men without the Word of God, were for a time received into the Church of God, [<hi>may be Changed] Mollified, Antiquated.</hi> And this too is ſo far from being there his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42329:7"/>
Majeſties peremptory Determination, that 'tis only ſaid, his Majeſty [<hi>Thinks, Conceives, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves</hi>] they may be antiquated. Whereas this Writer is not content to think our Church-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utions <hi>May be,</hi> but the whole ſcope of his Book is to prove they <hi>Ought</hi> to be alter'd and antiquated.</p>
            <p>3. That which his Majeſty is ſaid to Believe, does in the quotation refer not to <hi>All,</hi> but only to <hi>Moſt</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Obſervations, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not evident from that quotation, That our Church-Ceremonial-Obſervations, are in the number of thoſe which the King Conceived might be antiquated.</p>
            <p>For which reaſons this firſt quotation ſignified little to this Writers purpoſe, ſuppoſing it a Candid and Impartial quotation, which becauſe I have not that Epiſtle by me, I have not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the opportunity of examining.</p>
            <p>But if this <hi>Prefacer</hi> has treated King <hi>James,</hi> in this Teſtimony, no more candidly and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly than he has. King <hi>Charles</hi> in the next, he has in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> play'd the Knave with two Kings. For hapning to have the [<hi>Exact Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections</hi>] by me, I conſulted the Kings Anſwer to that Remonſtrance of the State of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and there found (<hi>p.</hi> 26. of that Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) immediately after the words by him quoted,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42329:7"/>
theſe following:—<hi>Provided that this Caſe be attempted and purſued with that modeſty, temper, and ſubmiſſion, that in the mean time the Peace and Quiet of the Kingdom be not diſturbed, the Decency and Comlineſs of Gods Service diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, nor the Pious, Sober, and Devout Actions of thoſe Reverend Perſons, who were the firſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in the Bleſſed Reformation—ſcandaliſed, and defamed.</hi> Which Proviſo being added, does ſo cramp and conſine the Condeſcenſion ſpoken of in the former words, that they are on that account rendred inſignificant to the Writers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and ſo they are upon another. For they only ſay, That his Majeſty <hi>would willingly</hi> comply with the Advice of a Parliament, for the making a Law to Exempt Tender-Conſciences from Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment or Proſecution; but does not ſay, either that 'twas [<hi>the duty</hi>] of a Parliament to give him ſuch Advice, nor that [<hi>it was his own duty</hi>] to comply with it when given: and yet nothing leſs than this will ſuffice to make this, or any other Teſtimony pertinent and adequate to this Authors attempt.</p>
            <p>For which reaſon therefore his next Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from the Declaration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, is as inſignificant to his purpoſe as this: For neither in that from <hi>Breda,</hi> nor in the other concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, does his Majeſty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42329:8"/>
Acknowledge it <hi>his Duty at that time</hi> not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the uſe of the Ceremonies on Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: nor if he had, would it thence follow, either that it is, or that his Majeſty thinks it his duty [<hi>now</hi>] to gratifie them by ſuch an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and yet even this alſo is requiſite to make Teſtimonies pertinent to our Authors deſign; which (as himſelf words it <hi>p.</hi> 4. of his Book) is to prove that <hi>things indifferent which may be changed and altered without Sin, or violation of Gods Laws, ought not, eſpecially under our preſent Circumſtances, to be impoſed by Superiors as the Conditions of Communion: or as Conditions without which none ſhall miniſter in ſacred things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, who that has any ſenſe of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and obligations of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>Civility,</hi> can think it tolerable in any man, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in a Church-man as this Author is ſaid to be) to treat the King at this rate, and to urge this Declaration in the behalf of Diſſenters now, when tis ſo well known that his Majeſty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thought fit to vacate it within two years after its publication, by conſenting to the Act of Parliament for Uniformity: which Act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us that <hi>his Majeſty had duly conſidered the Book of Common-Prayer, as then framed</hi> (which re-impoſed the uſe of the Ceremonies) <hi>and had fully approved and allowed the ſame, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42329:8"/>
it to that Parliament, that the ſaid Book—ſhould be Appointed to be uſed—under ſuch Sanctions and Penalties as the Houſe of Parliament ſhould thing fit</hi>—From which Approbation and Conſent of his Majeſty, we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that he was then made very ſenſible how unworthy the Diſſenters were of that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which he at firſt deſigned them, and how miſchievous 'twould prove to the Concerns both of Church and State: and that 'twas neither juſt nor reaſonable it ſhould be allowed them. And accordingly that Act aſſures us, that <hi>nothing conduceth more to the ſetling of the Peace of this Nation—nor to the honour of our Religion, and the Propagation thereof, then an univerſal Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Publick Worſhip of Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An excellent determination this! and a very golden ſentence! and yet this Gentleman pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends humbly to conceive the quite contrary (<hi>p.</hi> 8.) and to think that <hi>the united Judgement of the whole Nation cannot frame a better or a more unexceptionable Expedient for a firm and laſting Concord, then the Liberty indulged by the Kings Declaration,</hi> which required neither Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, nor Subſcription, nor Oath of Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Obedience.</p>
            <p>But I confeſs he ſpeaks there of an Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a firm and laſting Concord of theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42329:9"/>
               <hi>diſtracted Churches</hi>] by which expreſſion what the man means would perhaps be worth the knowing: and the rather becauſe the word [<hi>Churches</hi>] is printed in a different Character. A ſuſpicious man may reaſonably enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that he honours the <hi>Conventicles of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts</hi> with the Name of <hi>Churches,</hi> in oppoſition to Canon 10. before cited; if not, what Churches in <hi>England</hi> are ſo diſtracted, as to render his unexceptionable Expedient neceſſary to their Concord?</p>
            <p>But is not that a very pleaſant Queſtion which he puts (<hi>p.</hi> 9.) If <hi>as the Kings Royal Word aſſures us, the Reverend Biſhops in the Year 60. did think ſuch Conceſſions made by his Royal Perſon, and Authority, to allay the (then) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtempers very Juſt and Reaſonable, and cheerfully would conform themſelves thereunto, why ſhould we now conceive they ſhould be of another mind in</hi> 82?</p>
            <p>To which Queſtion I Anſwer ſeriouſly,</p>
            <p>1. That the Kings Royal Word, as quoted by this Writer (<hi>p.</hi> 6.) does not aſſure us that the Biſhops [<hi>did] then think ſo,</hi> but only <hi>that his Majeſty had not the leaſt doubt but that they would think ſo.</hi> However, on ſuppoſition he had quoted the Kings Words truly <hi>p.</hi> 39. I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, 2. We may well conceive it, becauſe his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42329:9"/>
Majeſty himſelf was of another mind in 62. and appears now to be of the ſame mind he was then, being ſo far from indulging, that he commands the Laws to be vigorouſly executed againſt Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>But does this man indeed fancy that the Caſe and Reaſon of things, is the ſame now in 82. that thoſe parts of the King's Declaration which he has quoted, repreſent it to have been in 60? Has he the Simplicity to believe himſelf, or the Confidence to deſire others to believe, that the Diſſenters are as innocent now, as that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion acquaints us, his Majeſty then found thoſe whom he Confer'd with?</p>
            <p>Can he tell us where theſe Presbyterians are now to be met with, who <hi>ſhew themſelves</hi> (as it ſeems thoſe did at the time there ſpoken of) <hi>Perſons full of Affection towards the King, or Zeal for the Peace of the Church and State, and neither Enemies to Epiſcopacy, nor Liturgy, but modeſtly deſire ſuch Alterations in either, as without ſhaking the Foundations, may beſt allay the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtempers?</hi> or can he tell us, where thoſe men of other Perſuaſions are now to be found, who <hi>all approve Epiſcopacy, and a ſet Form of Lyturgy? (p.</hi> 6.)</p>
            <p>Nay, have not the Leaders of ſeveral Parties ſadly demonſtrated themſelves to be men of a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42329:10"/>
quite contrary temper, ſince the diſcovery of the Popiſh Plot? ſome employing the beſt Reaſon, ſome the beſt Wit they had, others the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Arts that a lying, ſlandring, ſpiteful, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious humor could ſupply them with, to the prejudice of our Church and its Conſtitutions, and to the rendring not only its <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> but alſo its <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Lyturgy,</hi> Odious and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous.</p>
            <p>But whatever others may poſſibly think of our Biſhops, and their averſeneſs from condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in matters of Ceremony, this Prefacer, <hi>p.</hi> 9. proſeſſes to think with the <hi>Reverend Dean of</hi> Canterbury, that <hi>we have no cauſe to doubt, but the Governours of our Church are Perſons of that Piety, and Prudence, that for Peace ſake, and in order to a firm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion among Proteſtants, they would be content, if that would do it, not to inſiſt on little things, but yield them up to the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, or importunity of thoſe that differ from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Paſſage having been long ſince inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly deſcanted upon (in a Polio-Pamphlet, whoſe Title I cannot now call to mind) I ſhall let it paſs, but not without this Profeſſion, that I hope there is now no one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nor [<hi>would-be-Biſhop</hi>] Living, who would yield, and yield, and yield up ſo much of the Church-Conſtitutions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42329:10"/>
to Diſſenters, till he has left the Diſſenters nothing to yield up to the Church.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 10. the Learned and Judicious Judge <hi>Hale,</hi> is brought in as a Favourer of Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to moderate Non-conformiſts; and as one who drew up a Bill for Comprehenſion of ſome, and a limited Indulgence to others. And this we are told upon the Credit of Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> whoſe Teſtimony <hi>Valeat quantum valere poteſt.</hi> Nay, he is brought in as one who declar'd it his Judgement, That <hi>the only means to heal us was a new Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, which ſhould neither leave all at Liberty, nor impoſe any thing but Neceſſary</hi>—And this we are told upon the Credit of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who, I doubt, may ſay as the Dr. aforeſaid does of himſelf (in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face <hi>p.</hi> 8. to his <hi>Hiſtory of the Rights of Princes) I know this will not be the more believed for my ſaying it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that 'tis not naturally Impoſſible that ſuch words ſhould be ſpoken by Judge <hi>Hale,</hi> who can deny? but that he did actually declare his judgement in thoſe Terms, who can believe, that is at all acquainted with the Parts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals of that Great Man?</p>
            <p>For ſure he had more Wit than to call that an <hi>Act for [<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi>] which would leave
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42329:11"/>
men at Liberty, as to the Order, Modes, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and Ceremonies of Publick Worſhip; and more Conſideration than not to reflect that an Act which impoſes nothing but what's Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, will certainly leave men to that Liberty; and a Perſon of more Skill in the meaſures of Government, and the needs of Human Society, than to propoſe That, as the only means for the healing the breaches of this Nation in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, which was never yet made uſe of for the Cementing of any National So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men, or the effecting Union and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among them.</p>
            <p>For I dare Challenge this Author (if I had the opportunity) to ſhew me where there is, or ever was ſuch a Society, whoſe Union, Order, and Government, was conſerv'd or deſign'd to be conſerv'd by <hi>the impoſing</hi> on them <hi>nothing but neceſſary things:</hi> meaning by [<hi>neceſſary things</hi>] ſuch only as God's Word has made ſo, and as are contra-diſtinguiſh'd to all things in their own nature Indifferent; and ſo this Prefacer muſt underſtand this Teſtimony, if it be pertinent to the deſign of his Book.</p>
            <p>The 16. 17. and 18. Pages are taken up wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Opinion touching this Affair; which becauſe I had occaſion to conſider ſoon after that Book of his [<hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42329:11"/>
of Separation</hi>] was publiſh'd, I ſhall now impart to you the reſult of that conſideration; which was</p>
            <p>1. That if any one ſhould affirm That that Preface of the Doctors had deſtroyed what he had ſaid for our Church in his Book: And 2. That it has effectually deſtroyed that Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he had taken pains to defend in his Book: I did not ſee how the Doctor could purge himſelf from the Accuſation.</p>
            <p>In the third Part of the Book, and twenty ſixth Section, the <hi>Doctor</hi> defends our Churches Terms of Communion, and proves that there's no Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs in them; particularly not in <hi>the ſign of the Croſs, Kneeling at the Communion, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Obſervation of Holidays, the conſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Lyturgy,</hi> nor <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of God-Fathers, and God-Mothers in Baptiſm.</hi> The Lawfulneſs of all which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> except <hi>that of the conſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> which he Acknowledges-done very well to his hand by Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi> he defends by Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatſoever was urg'd againſt them by his Adverſaries. <hi>Pag. 332, 333. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet in the Preface, <hi>p.</hi> 83. he repreſents it as moſt adviſeable, either <hi>wholly to take away the Sign of the Croſs, or to leave it Indifferent as the Parents ſhall deſire, or not deſire:</hi> beſides which he would have Kneeling at the Sacrament diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42329:12"/>
with as to thoſe that ſcruple it—and ſeveral Alterations made in the ſetled Practice of our Church, as to the Uſe of God-Fathers and God-Mothers in Baptiſm. And to juſtifie this changing of our Church-Conſtitutions, he makes uſe of ſuch a Motive and Argument, as the truth is, if it prove any thing, proves thoſe Conſtitutions unlawful, and therefore that they ought to be aboliſh'd.</p>
            <p>For, 1. What leſs than this can reaſonably be inferr'd from theſe words of his, <hi>p. 82. I do think it would be a part of Chriſtian Wiſdom and Condeſcenſion in the Governours of our Church, to remove thoſe Barrs</hi> (that is, the matter of the Diſſenters ſcruplings and excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings againſt the Sacramental Offices) <hi>from a freedome in joyning in full Communion with us.</hi>] The moſt obvious and pertinent meaning of which words is, That it is ſuch a part of Wiſdome and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as Chriſtianity obliges our Governors to; and if they are obliged to it by vertue of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, it is certainly their duty to be ſo Wiſe and Condeſcending.</p>
            <p>But 2. in the immediately preceding Lines, he urges this Argument for that Condeſcenſion; (<hi>viz.</hi>) becauſe <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Sacraments in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church [ought] to be the moſt free from all Exception;</hi> and they [<hi>ought] to be ſo Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42329:12"/>
as rather to invite, than diſcourage ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Perſons from joyning in them.</hi> Which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, if valid, will effectually deſtroy, not only the preſcription of thoſe Ceremonies, but ſeveral other things of the like kind, which <hi>the men of Scruples</hi> are, or ſhall be pleaſed to except againſt; particularly, 'twill be as valid againſt the Uſe of a ſet Form of words in thoſe and other ſacred Adminiſtrations, becauſe even that, diſcourages abundance of ſcrupulous Perſons from joyning in any of the Publick Services of our Church; all which therefore will be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually deſtroyed by that Argumentation.</p>
            <p>Beſides which, he mentions <hi>p.</hi> 92. ſeveral other mutations for the ſatisfaction of the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, which <hi>p.</hi> 93. he thinks reaſonable to be allowed in order to an Union, As <hi>the explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or amending ſome more doubtful and obſcure paſſages in the Common-Prayer-Book; the uſe of the New Tranſlation of the Pſalms, (in Parochial Churches at leaſt) the charging of the Apochry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha-Leſſons, for portions of Canonical Scripture; the leaving at liberty thoſe Expreſſions in the Office for Burial, which ſuppoſe the good Eſtate of the Perſon buried: the reſtoring the Rubrick about the Salvation of Infants, to its former place in the Office of Confirmation, and ſo removing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent exceptions againſt it:</hi> by which laſt I confeſs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42329:13"/>
I do not well know what he means; becauſe I do not diſcern how the placing it in the Office of Confirmation, will remove the preſent ſcruples againſt it; thoſe ſcruples being about its truth; and the Propoſition contain'd in that Rubrick will certainly be no truer in one Office, than in the other.</p>
            <p>Now ſince 'tis plain that the Preface does thus endeavour to undermine and deſtroy ſo many of our Church-Conſtitutions, which yet the Book endeavours to uphold and maintain; and ſince he does it by an Argument which if rational and cogent, does as plainly infer the continuing thoſe Conſtitutions, eſpecially thoſe of them that belong to the Sacraments, to be no part of Chriſtian Wiſdom and Condeſcenſion in our Governours, but inconſiſtent with it, and with that freeneſs, from all exceptions, which ought to be the conſtant Attendant of thoſe Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I think 'tis evident that the Preface does, at leaſt virtually, and conſequentially, deſtroy, and render unlawful what the Book defends as lawful.</p>
            <p>Nay I do not diſcern what conſiſtency there is between one part of the Preface, and another part; between the <hi>allowing the fore-mentioned mutations as reaſonable and neceſſary, (Pag.</hi> 82. and 93.) and this paſſage, <hi>Pag.</hi> 89. which implies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42329:13"/>
they are neither neceſſary nor reaſonable. For there he ſays, [<hi>we do heartily and ſincerely deſire <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with our Brethren, if it may be had on juſt and reaſonable Terms; but they muſt not think that we will give up the Cauſe of the Church for it, ſo as to condemn its Conſtitution, or make the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies unlawful which have been hitherto ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and practiſed in it: if any Expedient can be found out for the Eaſe of other mens Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without reflecting on our own; if they can be taken in without Reproach, or diſhonour to the Reformation of the Church, I hope no True Son of the Church of</hi> England <hi>will oppoſe it.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Now whether the fore-mention'd diſpenſings with, and Retrenchments of our Church-Orders and Practices, upon the fore-mention'd Reaſon and Argument for the ſake of Union with them, whom he is pleas'd to call <hi>Brethren;</hi> be not ſo far a giving up the Cauſe of the Church, as to condemn its Conſtitution, and to make the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies unlawful, which have hitherto been obſerved and practiſed in it, I leave you to judge; as alſo whether the taking in Diſſenters upon ſuch Terms, will not neceſſarily reflect reproach and diſhonour upon the Reformation of that Church, which at her firſt Reforming thought fit to retain and impoſe thoſe Conſtitutions and Ceremonies as juſt and reaſonable, and as ſuch
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42329:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath ever ſince continu'd them, without imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that continu'd Impoſition, inconſiſtent with Chriſtian Wiſdom, or with any regard that's juſtly due to the Scruples and Exceptions of troubleſome men, relating to the Adminiſtration of Sacraments in a Chriſtian Church. To which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Men the <hi>Dr.</hi> is pleaſed to give the Title of [<hi>Brethren</hi>] more than once in the later end of the Preface, which is it ſelf, in my Opinion, too abſurd a contradiction to that Book, whoſe main deſign is to prove them <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He tells us <hi>Pag.</hi> 364. That <hi>'twas the great Wiſdom of our Church, not to make more things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as to Practice, than were made ſo at the Settlement of the Reformation; but whether there be ſufficient reaſon to alter thoſe Terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which were then ſettled, for the ſake of ſuch whoſe Scruples are groundleſs, and endleſs, I do not</hi> (ſays he) <hi>take upon me here to determin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I wiſh he had not taken it upon him in the Preface; eſpecially to determin it, ſo much to the Reproach and Diſhonour of our Church, as to imply ſhe hath hitherto been guilty of Tranſgreſſing the Obligation of Chriſtianity, in not making thoſe Alterations for the ſake of Union, with ſuch Perſons whoſe Scruples are groundleſs and endleſs, and <hi>which</hi> (as himſelf Affirms <hi>p. 372.) might be remov'd by a little Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42329:14"/>
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lue conſideration;—there being no depth of Learning, no ſubtilty of Reaſoning, no endleſs quotation of Fathers neceſſary about them; but the diſpute lies in ſuch a narrow compaſs, that men may ſee light if they will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why ours, or indeed any Church ſhould be Reproached as Defective in Chriſtian Wiſdom, for not complying with ſuch humerſom Perſons, or not altering her Conſtitutions for the ſake of ſuch wilfully blind and perverſe Diſſenters, I confeſs I do nor underſtand.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Premiſes being duly conſider'd, do I think abundantly juſtifie the firſt charge, and make it too reaſonable to adhere to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that <hi>the Doctors Preface hath deſtroyed what he had ſaid for our Church in his Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in reference to the other charge, that <hi>the Preface has effectually deſtroy'd that Church of</hi> England <hi>which the Doctor had taken pains to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in his Book.</hi> The ſame premiſes do really contribute ſo much to the making it good, that (for ought I ſee) no more need to be added to that End, than the bare application of them to that Cenſure, and to the Doctor's own Notion of <hi>the Church of</hi> England. For he aſſerts <hi>p.</hi> 249. of his Book, that <hi>the National Church of</hi> England <hi>diffuſive, is the whole Body of Chriſtians in this Nation, conſiſting of Paſtors and People, agreeing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42329:15"/>
in that Faith, Government and Worſhip, which are Eſtabliſh'd by the Laws of this Realm.—And Pag. 302. All Biſhops, Miniſters, and People, taken together, who profeſs the Faith ſo Eſtabliſh'd, and worſhip God according to the Rules ſo Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, make up this National Church of</hi> England. And this is [the Church of <hi>England</hi>] which <hi>the Doctor</hi> has taken pains to defend in his Book.</p>
            <p>If therefore <hi>the Church of</hi> England takes its denomination not only from the Profeſſion of that Faith, but alſo <hi>from its conſent in Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, according to ſuch and ſuch Rules,</hi> he that would deſtroy <hi>thoſe Rules,</hi> will conſequently deſtroy that Church, which is denominated ſuch, and diverſified from <hi>other Churches,</hi> by <hi>its em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing and adhering to thoſe Rules.</hi> But it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the premiſes, that the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face would have ſeveral conſiderable Alterations made of thoſe Rules, and that upon ſuch an account, and for ſuch reaſons, as do conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially deſtroy that Order, and thoſe Rules of Worſhip that are Eſtabliſhed by Law; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Preface does effectually deſtroy <hi>that Church of</hi> England which he had taken pains to defend in his Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are all the things,</hi> (ſays the Dr.) <hi>which appear to me reaſonable to be Allowed in order to an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion: and which I ſuppoſe may be Granted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42329:15"/>
without detriment, or diſhonour to our Church; And</hi> (ſays this Writer) <hi>theſe are all I plead for in this Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 1. there is this little difference between theſe Authors; The <hi>Reverend Dean</hi> ſuppoſes they [may be] Granted, but this Author endeavours to prove they [ought] to be Granted.</p>
            <p>2. Though that Author mentions only ſuch and ſuch things as appearing to him reaſonable to be Allowed, yet to make them appear ſo to others, he urges an Argument which will infer it as reaſonable to diſpenſe with a great many other things not mention'd. And ſo though this Author pretends that theſe are all he pleads for in his Book, yet the Arguments he makes uſe of, if they prove any thing, prove it the duty of our Governours to diſpenſe with a great many more Conſtitutions; even all that enjoyn any Indifferents, whereby our Brother is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. (<hi>Chap.</hi> 3.)</p>
            <p>And therefore whereas he adds here: <hi>As for thoſe who deny the lawfulneſs of Lyturgy, and the right Conſtitution of our Churches, and who would be exempted from the Juriſdiction of their Biſhop, and ſet up Congregations ſeparate and independent upon him; I know not how to plead for them, without pleading for Schiſm, Confuſion and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42329:16"/>I doubt his Arguments will, if they prove any thing, prove it as unlawful for Governours to impoſe a Lyturgy, and require Obedience to Epiſcopal Government, as to impoſe Ceremonies. For I am confident he is very ſenſible that a great many whom he ſeemed to account <hi>weak Brethren,</hi> are mightily offended with thoſe Conſtitutions alſo: And I doubt himſelf is not ſo ſtrong and hardy, as to affirm that our Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Dioceſan Epiſcopacy, are things foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on a Divine unchangeable Law. And if they be not, his Arguments will conclude againſt them, as well as againſt the impoſition of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</p>
            <p>As for the Teſtimonies which follow <hi>pag. 23. 24. &amp;c.</hi> my Remarks on them are theſe:</p>
            <p>1. Some of them I confeſs ſeem to ſpeak home to this Author's deſign: and pretend that our Ceremonies <hi>ought to be aboliſh</hi>'d: but if this Man's Book be fraught with no better Reaſons to prove it than thoſe mention'd by him, out of the Epiſtles of <hi>Judicious Beza,</hi> and <hi>Learned Zanchy,</hi> I'll be bold to ſay that it is good for little, but to prove the Author a very weak Brother.</p>
            <p>2. He ſhewed himſelf too near of kin to ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brother, in pretending <hi>pag.</hi> 23. That <hi>Calvin</hi> ſtyl'd our Ceremonies <hi>Follies,</hi> but owning that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42329:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
affirmed them <hi>Tolerable Follies,</hi> and then writing a great Book himſelf to prove them intolerable. But as to that Cenſure which <hi>Calvin</hi> is ſaid to paſs upon our Ceremonies, ſee <hi>Durell's [Vindiciae Eccleſiae Anglicanae] Cap.</hi> 12. where he makes it more than probable, That that Cenſure was not meant of our Ceremonies, nor of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lyturgy as it wa in it ſelf at that time: but as it was knaviſhly repreſented to him by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sectaries of thoſe days.</p>
            <p>3. I obſerve that ſeveral of his Teſtimonies <hi>pag. 38. &amp;c.</hi> ſeem not to ſpeak of the duty of the Governours, of this or that particular Church, to bear with, and indulge the Members of their own Church, in matters indifferent, but of the Duty (only) of one Proteſtant Church (<hi>pag.</hi> 40. 41.) towards another: <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>if both Churches agree in Fundamentals—their differences in other matters may be Tolerated. (pag. 38. 40.) The Reformed Churches,</hi> ſay the <hi>Geneva</hi>-Doctors, (<hi>pag. 40.) ought to maintain a Brotherly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards one another, &amp;c.—The Proteſtant-Churches,</hi> ſays the Tranſylvanian, (<hi>pag. 41.) are to be mov'd, notwithſtanding their differences, to exerciſe Moderation, Compaſſion, and Mutual Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>—And ſo the Profeſſors of <hi>Aberdeen, (pag.</hi> 42. 43.)</p>
            <p>The poſſibility of this Exception the <hi>Prefacer</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:42329:17"/>
himſelf was aware of, and therefore endeavours to enervate it, <hi>pag.</hi> 57. by Asking, <hi>What reaſon can be given why theſe conditions of Communion betwixt Reformed Churches, ſhould not obtain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Member of the ſame Chriſtian Church?</hi> And <hi>pag. 58. Why that Agreement in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, which is ſufficient to preſerve Communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Churches diſagreeing in Rites and Ceremonies, and Doctrines of inferior moment, may not be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent alſo to preſerve Communion among the members of the ſame Church, though diſagreeing in like matters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if there where no difference, between two Societies, neither of which is ſubject to, or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant upon the other, nor have any Governour common to them both; and the members of the ſame Society, or ſeveral Societies united under, and ſubject to ſuch or ſuch a Governour, or Governours. Where two Societies are indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent one upon another, there being no common Governour to take care of Order, and the things relating to it among them; each of them is left to the management of its reſpective Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Governours; and to them the care of the Publick Worſhip to be perform'd by that Society belongs; who therefore ought to ſee that it be performed in an orderly, decent, and reverent manner, and to conſtitute ſuch Modes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42329:17"/>
Rites and Ceremonies, as they judge moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to that End: And when they have ſo done, what has any other Church, which, in the Caſe ſuppos'd, cannot juſtly pretend to any ſuperiority over them, I ſay, what has ſuch a Church to do to call in queſtion their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions? in any Authoritative way, I mean. And therefore to talk of its being the duty of one Proteſtant Church to [<hi>tolerate</hi>] another, that's Independent upon it, and differs from it in matters of outward Order, is, at leaſt, a very improper way of ſpeaking. If by [<hi>tolerating</hi>] thoſe Teſtimonies mean only that they ſhould not Cenſure and Condemn the other Church that ſo differs from them, and if this Writer be of the ſame mind in this with the Authors of thoſe dictates, (and if he be not, why does he quote them as Teſtimonies favouring his pretenſions?) then himſelf ought to pronounce <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Zanchy,</hi> a little too pragmatical in quarrelling <hi>the Governours of the Church of</hi> England, for their thinking fit to retain ſuch and ſuch Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>But what does this Prefacer mean by [<hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Communion</hi>] and [<hi>Preſerving Communion</hi>] in theſe queſtions? Does it follow that becauſe theſe Teſtimonies make it the Duty of one Proteſtant Church ſo far to Accord with another,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42329:18"/>
that agrees with it in Fundamentals, and differs from it only in Rites and Ceremonies, or other matters extra-Fundamental, as [<hi>not faſtidiouſly to reject, or Anathematiſe that Church. P.</hi> 43.] on Account of any ſuch difference, that therefore they make it the duty of each Church to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the members of the other Church, to [<hi>all ſorts] of Communion</hi> meerly becauſe <hi>they agree in Fundamentals?</hi> If he fancy that to be their meaning, let him inſtance if he can in any one <hi>Proteſtant Church,</hi> that will receive others to <hi>Sacramental Communion</hi> meerly becauſe they hold the Fundamentals of Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>This Man has undertaken to maintain, That things Indifferent ought not to be impoſed as Conditions of Communion, or as Conditions without which none ſhall partake of the publick Ordinances; but does he imagine that if he go to <hi>Geneva,</hi> he ſhall be admitted to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion there without ſubmitting to the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Reception,</hi> there enjoyn'd? in particular, that they'll give it him unleſs he [ſtands] when he receives it? I am ſure <hi>Durell</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd <hi>Vindiciae, Cap.</hi> 22. where he defends the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> impoſing Kneeling on all Communicants, tells us that in that it chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges no greater a Power to it ſelf, than other Reformed Churches do. (<hi>pag.</hi> 235.) And that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42329:18"/>
as the Churches of <hi>the Lutheran Confeſſion</hi> will give the Communion only to thoſe that <hi>Kneel;</hi> ſo the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Geneva Churches</hi> will give it to none but ſuch as <hi>Stand</hi> in the Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving.</p>
            <p>Whereas therefore this Author would gladly know (<hi>pag. 58.) Why that Agreement in Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals, which is ſufficient to preſerve Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion betwixt Churches diſagreeing in Rites and Ceremonies—may not be ſufficient alſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Communion among the Members of the ſame Church, though diſagreeing in ſuch Matters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That the Communion which his own Teſtimonies ſpeak of as preſerv'd thereby, is only (for ought I ſee) that which conſiſts in <hi>not Cenſuring and Anathematiſing, or Diſowning them as True Churches,</hi> though differing in ſuch matters; which as it ſcarce deſerves the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Communion,</hi> ſo 'tis too far remov'd from the <hi>Nature</hi> of that <hi>Communion</hi> which this Book pleads for, to make theſe Teſtimonies pertinent to that Plea.</p>
            <p>And whereas he pretends in the ſame Page, that the reaſon why Chriſtian Churches which do thus differ, ſhould be received and owned as Chriſtians, and Brethren of the ſame Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us is, <hi>becauſe theſe differences do not hinder their being real Members of Chriſt's Body,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42329:19"/>
I Anſwer, by denying that to be the true, and adequate Reaſon; for the true Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the Caſe ſuppoſed of two Churches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent one on the other, and not ſubject to any Common Governour, the one Church has no Power to impoſe Rites and Ceremonies on the other, and conſequently no ſufficient ground to quarrel with it meerly for diſagreeing from it in matter of Ceremony: but if any of the members of one of the Churches refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Rites appointed by their own proper Governours, their Agreement in Fundamentals is no ſufficient ground why either their own, or the other Church, ſhould <hi>receive them to Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays indeed, that <hi>thoſe Differences do not hinder their being real Members of Chriſts Body:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 1. does he hold that every one who is really a member of Chriſts Body, ought <hi>eo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> to be admitted to all the Privileges of Chriſtian Communion? if he does, he muſt either deny that any real member of Chriſts Body can do any notorious wrong to his Neighbour by word or deed, or elſe he muſt condemn our Church for requiring the Miniſter of each Pariſh to repell ſuch a Perſon from the Communion, till either he makes actual recompence for the Injury, or declare himſelf fully reſolv'd to do it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42329:19"/>
when conveniently he may. If not, then the meer conſideration that ſuch a man is really a a member of Chriſts Body does not oblige any (in whoſe Power it is) to admit him to all thoſe Privileges.</p>
            <p>2. Does he hold that meer agreeing in Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals is all that's required to the being a real member of Chriſt? If not, then neither is that ſufficient to qualifie a man for all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of Chriſtian Communion.</p>
            <p>3. I ſuppoſe he will not deny that there are <hi>Practical</hi> as well as <hi>Speculative</hi> Fundamentals; and I preſume he is of Opinion, That Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to our Lawful Governours, in things Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, is one of the Fundamentals of <hi>Practice.</hi> If he denies the former, he contradicts the Doctrin of ſome of his own Teſtimonies; which affirm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That <hi>there are Fundamental Articles of Faith; without which, Chriſtian Faith cannot ſubſiſt, nor. Everlaſting Life be obtain'd:</hi> and That <hi>there are</hi> (alſo) <hi>Fundamental Heads of Diſcipline. (p.</hi> 56.) and that <hi>thoſe are ſo which promote and maintain the means of Salvation, and without which we cannot live a Chriſtian Life.</hi> And that <hi>whoſoever periſhes, muſt be ſeparated from the Foundation by ſome Fundamental Error in Doctrin, or in Practice:</hi> which ſuppoſes that there are Fundamentals of Practice, as well as Belief.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42329:20"/>As to the latter, he confeſſes (<hi>pag.</hi> 187. of his Book) That <hi>in thoſe matters which are not apparently forbidden by the clear Word of God, men ought to yield Obedience to the Commands of their Superiours;</hi> and if he will own that they ought to do ſo <hi>on pain of Damnation,</hi> as I hope he will, then 'tis a <hi>Fundamental Duty,</hi> even in his own account. That Chriſtian therefore that does <hi>not think it ſuch a Duty,</hi> is by this Doctrin guilty of a <hi>Fundamental Error</hi> in reference to <hi>Chriſtian Practice;</hi> and he who does <hi>think it his duty,</hi> and does <hi>not Act accordingly,</hi> is guilty of a <hi>damnable Neglect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I deſire to know of this Author</p>
            <p>1. Whether <hi>meer agreeing to Fundamentals,</hi> whether of Belief, or Practice, that is, aſſenting to them, will conſtitute, and continue a man a real member of Chriſts Body, without, at leaſt, reſolving to Act accordingly, if there be not time for more, and the performance of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution if there be?</p>
            <p>2. Whether differences in the Fundamentals of Practice, will not hinder men from being real members of Chriſts Body?</p>
            <p>3. Whether though they agree in the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Practice, that is, own and aſſent to them, as matter of neceſſary Duty in order to Salvation, yet if they perſiſt in the Neglect of any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42329:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
part of ſuch Duty, they ought to be own'd by the Church, either as real members of Chriſt, or as Perſons, to whom belong all the Privileges of Chriſtian Communion? If he ſays they ought, I deſire to know</p>
            <p>4. Why they ſhould be acknowled'gd as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons rightly qualified for the Privileges of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity here, or its Rewards hereafter, who are either ſo Ignorant as not to know, or ſo negligent as not to Practiſe, that which Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity has made Fundamentally neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to be both Known and Practiſed?</p>
            <p>Particularly I would willingly be inform'd by this man, whether account the preſervation of the External Unity of the particular Church, whether <hi>National, Dioceſan,</hi> or <hi>Parochial,</hi> of which men are members, a Fundamental of Practice, or no. If he does, how can he account thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons real members of Chriſts Body, who are ſo far from preſerving that Unity in either of thoſe Churches, that they induſtriouſly deſtroy it in all of them: not ſubmitting themſelves to the Rules of Order and Government, appointed for either of them? If he does not, then why does he 1. expreſly Acknowledge, That <hi>Schiſms and Diviſions, do apparently diſſolve the Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> And 2. (by asking thoſe queſtions, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. of his Book) implicitely Acknowledge,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42329:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
That <hi>Perſons become Schiſmatical by refuſing to be One with us in Diſcipline, and by renouncing Communion with us in our Publick Worſhip, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing there be nothing Evil in it?</hi> And 3. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all <hi>Separate Congregations Schiſmatical, for their not being ſubject to the Government of our Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſans? p.</hi> 59. And then 4. Acknowledge the Sin of <hi>Schiſm</hi> to be an <hi>heinous, deſtructive, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Evil: one of thoſe fleſhly works, which they who do, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. (Chap. 2. pag.</hi> 24. 25.) It muſt follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from his own Principles and Conceſſions, That they who are guilty of Schiſm, are guilty of Erring in a Fundamental of Practice.</p>
            <p>Now ſince Schiſm is by his own Confeſſion ſo pernicious an Evil; ſince by his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, alſo refuſing to be <hi>One</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in Communion with its Publick Worſhip, is a Breach and Diſſolution of Church-Unity, ſince alſo refuſing ſubjection to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Dioceſan Biſhops, is diſſolving the Unity of Diſcipline, and therefore Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical; and ſince all ſeparate Congregations in this Nation, are in his own Opinion, guilty of Schiſm, 'tis evident<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>1. That the members of thoſe Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either do <hi>Not Agree in all the Fundamentals of Practice,</hi> or elſe do <hi>Not Act ſuitably to that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42329:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Agreement,</hi> but are ſo far from it, that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in Schiſmatical Practices, contrary to the dictate of their Judgement and Conſcience.</p>
            <p>2. That they are not of the ſame Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us, and</p>
            <p>3. That the Pleas which this Prefacer makes uſe of in their behalf, <hi>pag. 58. (viz.</hi>) Their Agreement in Fundamentals, and their being real members of Chriſts Body, are very inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, becauſe by diſſolving (as much as in them lie,) the Unity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and its Diſcipline, they practically differ in a Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental of Chriſtianity. And by being <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> they diſown themſelves to be Perſons of the ſame Communion with us, nay are guilty of a capital Error, and a cuſtomary Crime, which excludes men while impenitently perſever'd in, from the Kingdom of Heaven; and therefore they ought not while in thoſe circumſtances, to be accounted perſons of the ſame Communion with us, or real members of Chriſts Body.</p>
            <p>I have now conſider'd ſeveral things, which I thought fit to be taken notice of in this Preface, and in the many Teſtimonies quoted by the Prefacer, as ſo many juſtifications of the deſign of his Book. But how ill they are ſuited to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, at leaſt for the generality of them, is I think apparent enough from the Reflexions I have here
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42329:22"/>
made upon them. But I wiſh heartily I had been in or near ſome Library, where I might have had the opportunity of examining the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and conſulting the Authors quoted; for then poſſibly I might have diſcovered much more impertinency in the quotations, and inſincerity in the quoter.</p>
            <p>'Tis plain the Author has ingag'd himſelf in a very bold Attempt. He has undertaken to prove, That <hi>things indifferent, which may be changed and altered without ſin, ought not, eſpecially under our preſent Circumſtances, to be impos'd by Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours as the Conditions of Communion, or of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration in Sacred Things.</hi> And conſequently he has undertaken to prove, That all Churches or States, who have ſo impoſed Indifferents, have by that Impoſition, been guilty of violating the Law of God.</p>
            <p>To Excuſe which Attempt from the prejudice of Singularity, he pretends <hi>pag.</hi> 3. to ſtrengthen it in his Preface, againſt that and other preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, <hi>by the concurrent ſuffrages of many worthy perſons, both of our own and other Churches, who have declar'd themſelves</hi> (as he would perſwade us) <hi>to be of the ſame Judgment, and have purſu'd the ſame Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now beſides all that has been already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to thoſe Suffrages, if I had the opportunity
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42329:22"/>
of doing it, I would challenge the Author to evince, that any tolerable number of the Suffrages which he has produc'd, are pertinent and punctual to his deſign, as worded by himſelf.</p>
            <p>That deſign conſiſts of Two Parts, one more general; <hi>That things indifferent, which may be alter'd without Sin, ought not to be impos'd as the Condition of Communion, or miniſtration in Sacred Things.</hi> The other more particular, That <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially they ought not to be impos'd under our preſent Circumſtances, as the Conditions of Communion with us</hi> (of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>)</p>
            <p>The Suffrages produc'd to reſcue this deſign from the imputation of Singularity, (amount in the Contents of the Preface) to about 35. Now let him manifeſt if he can,</p>
            <p>1. That ſo much as one of thoſe Suffrages ſpeaks particularly of <hi>our [preſent] Circumſtances</hi> here in <hi>England.</hi> I mean thoſe Circumſtances, that were preſent to the publiſhing of his Book.</p>
            <p>2. Let him manifeſt if he can, That among his 35 Suffrages, there are ſo many as <hi>five</hi> that affirm it unlawful to make Indifferents, which are Alterable without Sin, the Conditions of Church-Communion, and Miniſtration. Nay I doubt he cannot manifeſt that ſo much as one of them comes fully up to this deſign of his Book: But if the major part, or two parts in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42329:23"/>
three of the Teſtimonies be impertinent, what ſhall we think of that man who has the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and conſcience to write at ſuch a rate, and pretend ſo much when the proof falls ſo intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſhort of the pretenſe?</p>
            <p>Beſides, if my memory fail me not, I have ſeen a Book heretofore, which Anſwer'd <hi>Creſſy,</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi>'s Sermon, meerly by quoting paſſages out of Authors extant before that Book of <hi>Creſſy</hi>'s, which contained ſufficient Anſwers to the moſt material parts of it. And I believe that this Author could have done the like in reference to this Preface; I mean, that he could have heaped up as many and as pertinent Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, out of the Writings of ſingle Perſons, and Acknowledgments of Church-Societies, in favour of this Poſition, That it is lawful to make things Indifferent which may be altered without Sin, the conditions of Church-Communion and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, as he has pretended here in favour of the Contradictory; and if he could, I leave it to you to judge with what ſincerity he could profeſs (<hi>Pref. pag.</hi> 1.) that he was <hi>moſt unwilling to do the leaſt diſ-ſervice to the Church of which he is a member,</hi> when he has in this Preface done it the grand diſ-ſervice of heaping up ſuch a multitude of (pretended) Teſtimonies againſt the lawfulneſs of her Practice, and omitting the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42329:23"/>
much greater number of pertinent Suffrages, which I have ſome reaſon to believe himſelf could have as eaſily produced in defence of that Practice.</p>
            <p>But this Profeſſion of his is very obnoxious upon another Account; for if he were at all ſincere in making it, what ail'd him 1. to Print his Book at ſuch a time? And 2. in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> At ſuch a time? when he Acknowledges (<hi>pag.</hi> 9.) that the Biſhops themſelves have neither any Power to make ſuch Conceſſions, as his Book would have to be made, no nor any Power to <hi>make any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals for the healing of our breaches, till by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Authority they meet in Convocation, for that end;</hi> And I do not think that this Gentleman had any proſpect of a Parliaments being called ſoon after the publication of his Book; or that it is an Article of his Faith, that his Majeſty may ſummon a Convocation to meet to that end, out of Parliament, and then what could the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of ſuch a Book at ſuch a time be, but the promoting on his part, that which has been of late the grand Fanatical Deſign of ſuch weak Brethren as <hi>Baxter, Alſop, Troughton,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> the rendring our Governors both in Church and State, odious by repreſenting their Conſtitutions as unlawful, and attempting to prove them contradictory both to the Commands and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> But what ail'd
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42329:24"/>
him 2. to compoſe and print his Book in <hi>Engliſh?</hi> was it becauſe he expected either a <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Convocation,</hi> whoſe major part ſhould be made up of Clergy-men, or Gentlemen ſo ill bred as not to underſtand <hi>Latin?</hi> or did not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor underſtand it himſelf ſo well as to write a Book in it? or did he publiſh it in <hi>Engliſh</hi> for the ſake of the weak Brethren, and the devout Siſters, that they might be furniſhed with Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt <hi>Ceremony-Impoſing-Laws,</hi> from one end of the Goſpels and Epiſtles, to the other? For he has ſhewed himſelf ſo dexterous in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning and multiplying prejudices, and excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt ſuch Conſtitutions, that 'tis to be hoped a little more improvement of his Topical Parts, may gain him <hi>Parker</hi>'s faculty of Eſpying in thoſe Impoſitions <hi>in general,</hi> as he did in the Uſe of the Croſs <hi>in particular,</hi> a contradiction to all the Ten Commandments.</p>
            <p>Now for a man to put forth ſuch a Book againſt thoſe Impoſitions for the ſake of illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, who 1. have no power at preſent to retrench, or null, the Impoſitions; nor 2. are ever like to have: who 3. are like to make a moſt miſchievous uſe of it, to the diſhonour, and prejudice of the Church, and yet to pretend himſelf <hi>moſt unwilling to do the leaſt diſ-ſervice to the Church,</hi> is ſo palpably
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42329:24"/>
               <hi>Proteſtatio contra factum,</hi> that hardly any thing can be more ſo.</p>
            <p>But why talks he only of doing diſ-ſervice to [<hi>the Church?</hi>] as if that only were concern'd, when the contents and deſign of his Book, caſt as great a ſlur upon, and tend as much to the reproach and diſparagement of [<hi>the State</hi>] as of [<hi>the Church;</hi>] for he knows well enough, that the Laws enjoyning Uniformity, and impoſing our Ceremonies, are made <hi>by the King,</hi> and that with the Conſent not only of the <hi>Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,</hi> but <hi>Temporal</hi> alſo, and <hi>the Commons,</hi> ſo that this Author in thus attempting to prove thoſe Laws repugnant to the Law of God, and inconſiſtent with ſo many of the grand momentous obligations of Chriſtianity, is ſo far from ſhewing himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to do diſ-ſervice to the <hi>Church,</hi> that he has ſpent a great deal of time and pains, and employed (as one may gueſs) the utmoſt of his Art and Induſtry, to do as great a diſ-ſervice <hi>to that, and the State both,</hi> as (for ought I know) he could poſſibly do it with his Pen; for what greater diſ-ſervice can there be done <hi>in that way</hi> to any Government, than to Aſſert and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Poſition, from which it follows by unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable conſequence; That the Governours of this or that Nation, have for multitudes of Years ſucceſſively agreed, in Enacting Laws contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42329:25"/>
to the Practice and Commands, the Exhortations, Arguings, and Examples of both Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>For this is the immediate conſequent of this Poſition, and his manner of proving it, That <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours ought not to impoſe things Indifferent and Alterable without Sin, as the Conditions of Church-Communion, and Miniſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, what greater Affront could be offer'd to <hi>the King himſelf,</hi> then to publiſh ſuch a Book, at that very time when <hi>His Majeſty</hi> gave ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of his Reſolutions to uphold and defend the Act for Uniformity, and of his Zeal for the <hi>Church,</hi> by requiring a ſtrict and vigorous Execution of the Laws againſt Diſſenters?</p>
            <p>This man's undertaking therefore thus manag'd, in contradiction to the Laws of the Land, at a time when the King himſelf and inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates were more induſtriouſly zealous in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thoſe Laws, than they have been for many years, is in my Opinion ſuch a daring and impudent pragmaticalneſs, as ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered and chaſtiſed with a Puniſhment as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious as the Crime.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially ſince, as was before intimated, I doubt not but this very Writer could have fill'd as many ſheets as this Preface contains, with Teſtimonies juſtifying the Conſtitutions of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42329:25"/>
our Church and State in matters indifferent; and I am confident, had I had but my own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary about me, three parts whereof are ſtill at <hi>Oxford,</hi> I could have done ſo my ſelf. But in ſome of the few Books I have here, I meet with ſuch paſſages, as abundantly confirm me in that Confidence; and withall make me very much ſuſpect this Prefacer's ſincerity and ingenuity, in quoting. For whereas he has in this Preface quoted <hi>Beza</hi> as an Enemy to all Symbolical Rites, (<hi>pag.</hi> 25) and affirming that <hi>they ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely excluded from the Chriſtian Church;</hi> and <hi>Zanchy</hi> as an Enemy to our Ceremonies—and beſides pretended <hi>pag.</hi> 35. That 'twere endleſs to ſet down all that <hi>Bucer, Calvin, Chamier, Daneus, Farel, Povanus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin,</hi> and <hi>Zipper, with many others; have ſaid againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of them,</hi> and [pag. 36.] <hi>that</hi> Caſſander <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies</hi> (without telling us where he ſo teſtifies) <hi>that moſt have conceiv'd them fit to be condemned and aboliſhed as foppiſh, ludicrous, ridiculous, yea as noxious and pernicious. Durell</hi> has given us ſuch a different Account of things, as is very oppoſite to this <hi>Prefacer</hi>'s pretenſions.</p>
            <p>For in his forementioned Book, <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. He Affirms that the Chriſtian Church, from the Apoſtles time to this day, was never without, nor <hi>in the judgment of the moſt Learned and Famous
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42329:26"/>
Proteſtants,</hi> either can or ought to be without ſome ſignificant Ceremonies, <hi>pag.</hi> 182. to which purpoſe he quoted the ſentiments of <hi>Luther, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi> and <hi>Calvin, pag.</hi> 186. and then ſaid: I could here produce very many more of the moſt Learned, and Renowned Perſons in the Reformed Churches, of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Luther, Melancthon</hi> and <hi>Calvin, in this point.</hi> Nor ſays he, do I remember to have read any Reform'd Writer of any Note, eſpecially of thoſe who were at the beginning of the Reformation, (whoſe Judgment and Authority is principally to be attended to in this diſpute) who Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns ſignificant Ceremonies meerly as ſuch, if ſo be no ſupernatural vertue be attributed to them, for the producing Spiritual Effects; nor Religion placed in them, nor Merit, or Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation expected from the uſe of them. Out of which number he do's not except <hi>Beza</hi> himſelf: but proceeds to Vindicate him as to that very Paſſage which this Prefacer has quoted out of his Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Grindal,</hi> (as if it were for his turn) and manifeſts that it ought not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ſuch Symbolical Rites as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to ſignifie only mens duty, but ſuch only as are meant to ſignifie and exhibit Spiritual Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and the Divine Grace. And in his <hi>Sixteenth Chapter,</hi> he largely Anſwers that <hi>Epiſtle
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42329:26"/>
of Zanchy,</hi> quoted at large by this Prefacer, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. &amp;c. againſt impoſing Linnen Garments, and moſt of his Anſwers are taken out of <hi>Calvin, Bucer, P. Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Zanchy</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>And as to our Churches retaining the Uſe of <hi>the Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> its <hi>Thirtieth Canon</hi> Acquaints us that <hi>That reſolution and practice hath been allowed and approved—by the Harmony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of later years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Aſſertion of the Compoſers of that Canon, and thoſe other of <hi>Durell</hi> as to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perſons approving the Impoſition of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, makes me very much ſuſpect this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's ingenuity, and honeſty in quoting.</p>
            <p>And I doubt he has contented himſelf with quoting many Teſtimonies (beſides thoſe out of <hi>Geſſelius,) pag</hi> 38. &amp;c. only by Retale, and at ſecond hand from others, without examining the quotations himſelf, and conſulting the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as they lye in the Original Authors; which is an intolerable Neglect in any man that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to Write and Publiſh a Diſcourſe and Preface, <hi>of this Nature and Conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And one quotation which makes me ſuſpect this, is that <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. and 46. out of <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Diſput. of Human Ceremonies. Chap.</hi> 24. (it ſhould be 14.) <hi>Sect. 3. R.</hi> 2. where he ſays: <hi>'Tis ſhrewdly Argued by Mr.</hi> Baxter (againſt our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42329:27"/>
Ceremonies)—<hi>This ſeems to be coming after Chriſt, to amend his Laws, correct his Works, and make better Laws and Ordinances for his Church, than he himſelf hath done; for if Chriſt would have ſuch Rites impoſed on the Churches, he could better have done it himſelf, than have left it to man; for theſe Rites are equally neceſſary, or unneceſſary throughout all Ages, and in all Places where Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity obtains. If Croſſing, Kneeling, Surplice, he needful to be uſed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>why not in all the Churches of the Saints? If they are needful or expedient, for Order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, for Reverence and Decency in this Age; Why not in that in which our Lord and his Apoſtles liv'd, and through all ſubſequent Ages of the Church? If therefore Chriſt did neither by himſelf nor his Apoſtles, who form'd the firſt Church, and deliver'd us his mind, inſtitute and impoſe theſe Rites, then either the impoſing them is needleſs, or elſe you muſt ſay that Chriſt hath omitted what was needful to the due performance of his Worſhip; which ſeemeth to imply<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that either he was ignorant what to do, or careleſs and neglective of his own Affairs: which cannot be Aſſerted without Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhrewd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Argument I confeſs, in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it; if allowed for a good Argument, but 'tis really ſo pitiful a Ratiocination, <hi>as to this Prefacer's deſign in quoting it,</hi> that I believe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42329:27"/>
               <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf has Wit and Reaſon enough ſtill left him, if ſtill living, to laugh at any man that ſhould be wheedl'd by it into a perſwaſion that it is unlawful for any Church or State, to impoſe ſuch and ſuch Rites and Ceremonies, as it thinks moſt convenient for Order, Uniformity, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and Decency, <hi>Becauſe thoſe Ceremonies were never impoſed by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which I mention it for is this, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt what kind of quoter this man hath ſhewn himſelf.</p>
            <p>Any Reader who views the quotation, and the lines of it mark'd each of them with two little hooks, may juſtly think that the lines ſo mark'd conſiſt only of <hi>Baxter</hi>'s words, and in the ſame order as diſpoſed by <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf in that Chapter, Section, and Reaſon: but it is ſo far from being ſo, that</p>
            <p>1. Theſe words [<hi>This ſeems to be coming after Chriſt, to amend his Laws, correct his Works, and make better Laws and Ordinances for his Church, than he himſelf hath done,</hi> are not <hi>Baxter</hi>'s words (in that Paragraph of that Diſputation, as Printed with the other four in 1659<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I believe is the only Edition of thoſe Diſputations of <hi>Church-Government</hi>) but this man's own; unleſs he has quoted them at ſecond hand from ſome falſifyer of Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:42329:28"/>2. Whereas in the quotation 'tis, <hi>If they</hi> (viz. Croſſing, Kneeling, Surplice) <hi>are needful or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for Order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, for Reverence, and Decency in this Age, why not in that in which our Lord and his Apoſtles liv'd, and through all ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Ages of the Church?</hi> this Clauſe alſo and Queſtion, is not Mr. <hi>Baxters,</hi> but this mans own or ſome body's that has impoſed upon him.</p>
            <p>3. Whereas the Prefacer concludes the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with theſe words [<hi>which cannot be Aſſerted without Blaſphemy] Baxter's</hi> words are (only) [<hi>which are not to be imagined,</hi>]</p>
            <p>Now 2. Neither of theſe variations are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in any Teſtimony that is publiſhed as a juſt and exact quotation, as any Reader would gueſs this to be, by the manner of printing it. But</p>
            <p>3. The ſecond Clauſe is ſuch an addition, as is altogether intolerable; for <hi>Baxter</hi> doth not there diſpute againſt the Ceremonies of Croſſing and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, conſidered <hi>as expedient for Order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, Reverence, and Decency.</hi> But as (things pretended by him to be) <hi>Myſtical, Symbolical, Sacramental Rites;</hi> and his reaſoning (ſuch as it is) is there directed againſt them <hi>only under that Notion:</hi> for this Author therefore to quote him as there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that reaſoning to our Ceremonies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as <hi>Needful or Expedient for Order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42329:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
&amp;c. is not to <hi>quote</hi> but to <hi>invent</hi> and <hi>falſifie,</hi> and therefore</p>
            <p>4. If the reſt of this Gentleman's quotations which I have not the opportunity of examining, are of the ſame complexion with this, he muſt in all reaſon be concluded either a Knaviſh quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelf, or a quoter at ſecond hand, from ſome body that was ſo.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing <hi>Baxter</hi> had reaſon'd ſo ſimply (as for ought I know he may in ſome other part of his writings) as this Prefacer makes him to do in that Paragraph, againſt mens appointing ſuch and ſuch Ceremonies, as needful for Order, Uniformity, Reverence, and Decency, I ſhall annex an wholſome <hi>Teſtimony-Antidote</hi> againſt the venom of it, which I find quoted to my hands from Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> (I hope with more honeſty and fidelity than this is Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) by Dr. <hi>Hooke</hi> (in his judicious Anſwer to <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Petition for Peace, pag.</hi> 150. in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us hold thsi, That if we ſee in every Society of men ſome Policy to be neceſſary, which may ſerve to nouriſh common Peace, and to retain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; if we ſee that in the doing of things there is always ſome Orderly Form which is behoveful for publick honeſty, and for very humanity not to be refus'd, the ſaine ought chiefly to be obſerv'd in Churches which are both beſt maintained by a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42329:29"/>
well-fram'd diſpoſition of all things, and without Agreement are no Churches at all. Therefore if we will have the ſafety of the Church well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, we muſt altogether diligently procure that which St.</hi> Paul <hi>commandeth, That all things be done Comely, and according to Order. But for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as there is ſo great diverſity in the manners of men, ſo great variety in minds, ſo great diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in judgements and wits, neither is there any Policy ſtedfaſt enough, unleſs it be Eſtabliſhed by certain Laws, nor any orderly uſage can be obſerved without a certain appointed Form; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are ſo far off from condemning the Laws that are profitable to this purpoſe, that we affirm that when theſe be taken away, Churches are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from their ſinews, and utterly deformed and ſcatter'd abroad; for this which St.</hi> Paul <hi>requireth, That all things be done decently and in Order, cannot be had, unleſs the Order it ſelf and Comelineſs, be Eſtabliſhed with obſervations ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned as with certain Bonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this only thing is always to be excepted in thoſe Obſervations. That they be not either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be neceſſary to Salvation, and ſo bind Conſciences with Religion, or be applyed to the Worſhip of God, and ſo Godlineſs be repoſed in them.—But (pag. 152.) it is good yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine more plainly what is comprehended under that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42329:29"/>
Comelineſs which</hi> St. <hi>Paul commendeth, and alſo what under Order. The end of Comelineſs is partly that when ſuch Ceremomies are uſed as may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Reverence to holy things, we may by ſuch helps be ſtirred up to Godlineſs: partly alſo, that the Modeſty and Gravity which ought to be ſeen in all honeſt doings, may therein principally appear. In Order, this is the firſt Point, That they which Govern may know the Rule and Law to Govern well, and the People which are governed may be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd to Obeying of God, and to right Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Then, that the ſtate of the Church being well fram'd, Peace and Quietneſs may be provided for. Verily becauſe the Lord hath in his holy Oracles both faithfully contain'd, and clearly ſet forth both the whole ſum of true Righteouſneſs, and all the parts of the Worſhipping of his Divine Majeſty, and whatſoever was neceſſary to Salvation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in theſe things, he is only to be heard as our School-Maſter. But becauſe in outward Diſcipline and Ceremony, his Will was not to preſcribe each thing particularly what we ought to follow, becauſe he foreſaw this to hang upon the ſtate of Times, and did not think one Form to be ſit for all Ages, herein we muſt flee to thoſe general Rules which he hath given, that thereby all thoſe things ſhould be tryed which the neceſſity of the Church ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to be Commanded for Order and Comelineſs.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42329:30"/>
Finally, foraſmuch as he hath therefore taught nothing expreſly, becauſe theſe things are not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, and according to the Manners of every Nation and Age, ought diverſly to be applyed to the Edifying of the Church, therefore as the Profit of the Church ſhall require, it ſhall be convenient as well to Change and Abrogate thoſe that be uſed, as to inſtitute New. I grant indeed, that we ought not raſhly, nor oft, nor for light Cauſes to run to Innovation, but what may hurt or edifie, Charity ſhall beſt judge, which if we ſuffer to be the Governeſs, all ſhall be ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now it is the duty of Chriſtian People, to keep ſuch things as have been ordain'd according to this Rule with a free Conſcience, and without any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, but yet with a godly and eaſie readineſs to obey, not to deſpiſe them, nor to paſs them over with careleſs negligence: ſo far is it off, that they ought by Pride and Obſtinacy openly to break them. What manner of Liberty of Conſcience, wilt thou ſay, may there be in ſo great Obſervation and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs? Yes, it ſhall ſtand excellently well: when we ſhall conſider, that they are not ſtedfaſt and perpetual ſtayed Laws whereunto we are bound, but outward rudiments for the weakneſs of men, which though we do not all need, yet we do all uſe them, becauſe we are mutually bound to one another, to nouriſh Charity among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:42329:30"/>Thus, ſays Dr. <hi>Hooke,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin delivers his judgment directly contrary to yours,</hi> (meaning <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter's, as expreſſed in that Petition for Peace) I add, and directly contrary to that which our <hi>Prefacer</hi> here quotes as his ſhrew'd Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but) <hi>perfectly conſentient to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and we find his practice according with his judgment; he put the Yoke of Diſcipline upon the Neck of the Senate and People of</hi> Geneva, <hi>and bound them to it with an Oath: and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares for a Form of Prayers and Eccleſiaſtical Rites, from which it may not be lawful for the Paſtors to depart in their Function.</hi>—</p>
            <p>You ſee hereby how far <hi>Calvin</hi> was from the Opinion, That Churches either <hi>ſhould be govern'd</hi> without Ceremonies, or indeed <hi>can be govern'd,</hi> if nothing be impoſed on their Members, but what is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>I know 'tis eaſie to dictate as ſome men are ſaid to do in this Preface, That <hi>all neceſſary things are ſo plain in Scripture, that men may ſoon agree in what is neceſſary, and conclude the no-neceſſity of agreeing in more. pag.</hi> 12.—That <hi>all things neceſſary to be believed, are done in order to acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance with God, are fully and perſpicuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Holy Scripture, and therefore 'tis unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to exact further of our Brethren, that which is confeſſed unneceſſary, and which neither our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42329:31"/>
Saviour, nor his Apoſtles impoſed on their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, (pag.</hi> 46.) That <hi>neceſſary points (pag. 20.) may and will by [all honeſt people] be known and determin'd by the clear Teſtimony of Scripture, by conſent of Fathers, by general Tradition.</hi>—(As if all honeſt People could find out the conſent of Fathers, or be ſo familiarly acquainted with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Tradition.) <hi>and other points need not to be determined.</hi>—That <hi>all Confeſſions of particular Churches ſhould be aboliſhed (pag. 53.) and one publick Symbol agreed on, which ſhould be expreſſed only in the words of Scripture, and want nothing which is neceſſary to Salvation, to be known or done, nor contain any thing which is not thus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation.—and in unneceſſaries there ſhould be a mutual bearing one with another—That conſent in Fundamentals ought to be carefully maintain'd, but in other things neglected. (pag. 55.) That there ſhould be nothing in our Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, that may give any plauſible pretence for Separation or Nonconformity—(pag.</hi> 21.)</p>
            <p>Now theſe, I confeſs, are ſeveral of them, very ſine Aerial Speculations; ſuch as is no very difficult thing for <hi>Mercurial Wits</hi> to light on; and 'tis as eaſie for any Melancholy, Contemplative Man, to warm his Brains into a conceit of their Truth, Worth, and Excellency. But <hi>loquere ut videam:</hi> I would fain ſee the Man that either
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42329:31"/>
has prov'd them, or can prove them to be <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Notions.</hi> I mean, ſuch as may be prudently applyed to the conſtituting or continuing of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, or to the maintaining of a publick conſent, or a common order and <hi>decorum</hi> among 'em. It may be a great Truth that <hi>all things neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation are plainly and clearly revealed in Scripture;</hi> but that they are all ſo plain that all may ſoon agree in what is neceſſary, or that all honeſt People may know and determin all ſuch points, or that only ſuch ſhould be agreed in and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd, I ſhall conclude to be very unpracticable Notions, till this Gentleman or ſomebody for him, can tell me <hi>Firſt,</hi> What Perſon, or Perſons, have ſo much as pretended to give an exact Liſt and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue in <hi>particular</hi> of all thoſe Fundamentals which <hi>in general</hi> we profeſs to Believe, plainly contain'd in Scripture. 2. Where that Society of Chriſtians is to be met with, which is govern'd only by union and conſent in things abſolutely neceſſary? Or 3. where that Proteſtant Church is to be found, where nothing of Ceremony is impoſed either for Order, Decency, or Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity?</p>
            <p>If no ſuch inſtance can be produc'd, 'tis a pregnant evidence that ſuch Theories and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, are inflexible to the meaſure and ends of Government, incompatible with the duty of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42329:32"/>
Governours, and with the neceſſities of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Societies that are to be govern'd; and therefore they ſeem calculated only for the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> or <hi>Cracovia,</hi> and may ſerve in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently for all <hi>Latitudinarian Regions,</hi> and <hi>Anarchical Routs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee, Sir, by this Packet how great a trouble your generoſity in ſending me [<hi>The Proteſtant Reconciler</hi>] has drawn upon you; no leſs than that of reading ſeveral Sheets of Animadverſions on the Preface; but you may comfort your ſelf with believing that your Trouble will end here, as mine does. For having not my own Books by me, ſcarce any of them I mean, that might be ſerviceable for ſuch a purpoſe, 'twill be a vanity for me to attempt the Confutation of the Prefacer's Book; eſpecially ſince he has been pleas'd to intereſs Dr. <hi>Womock</hi> (a much more conſiderable Perſon, and ſtill living I hope) in the Contents of it, inſomuch that if he ſhall think fit to make any Reply to him, his Book will, I believe, neither require, nor deſerve any other or better Confutation, than will reſult from that Defence. It was but the beginning of this Month that I receiv'd it from your kindneſs; and having ſince ſpent all this pains about the Preface, you cannot imagine I have ſo much as read the Book; But however, I have ſo far conſider'd the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42329:32"/>
Contents of its Chapters, and glanced upon ſo many parts of the Book, that I conjecture the main ſtreſs and turn of the Cauſe lies in the fourth Chapter, which therefore whoſoever ſolidly Anſwers, will effectually baffle the deſign of this Writer, and may let the reſt of the Book take its courſe; and permit the weak Brethren to make the beſt Advantage they can of it. When you have peruſed theſe Papers, I hope you will impartially communicate your ſenſe of them to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Cordial Friend, and Humble Servant, S. T.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 28. 1682 / 3.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
